<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Daydream on NanCunChild&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/tags/daydream/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Daydream on NanCunChild&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    
    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 23:16:10 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/tags/daydream/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Shortcut at Santa Fe</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/strange_dream_age_of_discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 23:16:10 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/strange_dream_age_of_discovery/</guid>
      
      <description>All compass lead to the same destination</description>
      
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>The stone walls of Santa Fe kept out the scorching heat of Granada, but the restlessness of war seeped right through the masonry. I, a Genoese, stood inside this fortress built for a siege. The family crest upon my chest might have carried some weight back home, but here, under the scrutinizing gaze of generational dukes, its significance was easily shaken. I felt like a pawn cast by the hand of Fate onto a chessboard near the endgame—insignificant among the major pieces. They were the masters of this land, while I was merely a lowly navigator, waiting like a hyena for them to toss me a scrap of opportunity.</p>
<p>Outside, a holy war that had lasted centuries was grinding on. In the veins of every Spanish noble present flowed the memories of hundreds of years of battling the Moors. Now, the finish line was in sight. Following their gazes as they unconsciously glanced out the window, I looked toward the dust-choked land scorched by war, where the silhouette of the Alhambra stood like an exquisite, fragile dream. The fanaticism of imminent victory and the gloom of an empty treasury mixed on every lord&rsquo;s face like two incompatible pigments. They spoke loudly of God’s glory and the surrender of the Sultan of Granada, as if the volume could drown out the hollow echo of their dry purses.</p>
<p>The Treasurer, the Duke de Guzman, whispered to Cardinal Mendoza and fell into deep thought. His weather-beaten face was harder than the stones of Santa Fe. Finally, he rapped his knuckles on the wooden table, silencing the great hall instantly. His grave voice cut through the crowd’s fantasies of war booty: &ldquo;Your Majesties, with the new loans from the Genoese bankers, the soldiers have bread for the week. But fodder for the knights&rsquo; horses has been halved, and we haven&rsquo;t scraped together the coin for the next cannon volley. Fighting like this&hellip; we are merely competing with the heathens to see whose granary runs dry first!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The temperature of the room’s fanaticism plummeted at this cold report of reality. Everyone’s eyes, intentionally or otherwise, began to drift toward me, and toward another—a &ldquo;Sage&rdquo; from the East. At this moment, they hoped that we, these humble travelers, could conjure a miracle that turned stone into gold.</p>
<p>Only then did I focus on this Eastern Sage. He wore silk robes cut in the local style, heavy wooden prayer beads around his wrists, and sported the characteristic goatee of an Oriental. His sparse hair was pulled into a strange bun atop his head, secured by a wooden hairpin. He looked neither like a priest nor like any heathen we knew.</p>
<p>The Duke de Guzman turned his gaze to the &ldquo;Sage,&rdquo; his eyes passing over me without even a pause. &ldquo;Master Zheng, you are the adopted son of the Great Ming Empire&rsquo;s Imperial Voyager, Zheng He, and you have conducted trade in the West. There should be no one better suited to explain the essentials of navigation and commerce.&rdquo;</p>
<p>These words drew looks of amazement from the nobles. They had heard of Zheng He’s name, and the miracles of the Ming’s great voyages were legendary across the four seas.</p>
<p>Master Zheng began to speak, his voice slow and steady. &ldquo;We have an old saying in the Great Ming: &lsquo;Kuafu chased the sun and died of thirst on the road; but he who waits by the stump for a rabbit can at least fill his belly for a meal.&rsquo; It means one should not pursue things that are ethereal and void&hellip;&rdquo;</p>
<p>As soon as he said this, the surrounding nobles nodded meaningfully. Some cast contemptuous glances at me. Hearing this argument from the Master was exactly what the nobles wanted; the subsequent evidence didn&rsquo;t matter anymore. He went on to say that going south and east was the true &ldquo;Mandate of Heaven.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After a speech on destiny, Master Zheng slowly stroked his goatee, tracing routes on the map. A shrewd, merchant-like light gleamed in his black eyes. As if revealing a cosmic secret, he whispered mysteriously: &ldquo;My Lords, the African route that the Portuguese have spent sixty years and countless lives of excellent sailors to open up—that is the greatest treasure. Let them continue to round the Cape of Good Hope like blind men. We shall be the clear-eyed ones following behind to pick up the gold scattered everywhere.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A ripple of low laughter spread through the hall—the knowing laughter that belongs to smart people. The heavy oppression regarding the fate of the nation vanished, replaced by a bloated sense of cleverness.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You mean&hellip; copy their route?&rdquo; A young baron leaned forward from the crowd, asking uncertainly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not at all,&rdquo; Master Zheng smiled, his tone carrying a hint of arrogance and affectation. &ldquo;It is to &lsquo;borrow&rsquo; their wisdom. This wisdom is God&rsquo;s gift to all mankind.&rdquo; Upon hearing the Master invoke God, the baron dispelled his doubts and nodded slowly.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Since the routes are charted and the ports built, we need only send nimble small vessels to avoid their main fleet. While they push south and east into unknown waters, we will stay in the safety of their rear ports, buying ivory and gold at ten percent less than they pay. Let them bear the risks of the unknown seas; we shall reap the profits of the known ports. This is also a wisdom from my home, the Great Ming, called &lsquo;Borrowing a Hen to Lay Eggs&rsquo;&hellip;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Amidst this torrential instillation of Ming wisdom, I wanted to say something, but the gaze of the Duke de Guzman cut me off. When Master Zheng finished, the Duke commented, &ldquo;This is a mature and prudent suggestion. Master Zheng’s foresight is admirable, far surpassing certain&hellip; shortsighted and untimely individuals.&rdquo; The deliberate pause made my face burn. &ldquo;What our Empire needs is certain gold, not ethereal legends from beyond the ocean. I trust no one disagrees. Now, let us discuss the details of the voyage.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was then I remembered: in this palace filled with inflated arrogance and hubris, my weight was like a feather, while the ministers who held power and wished to reuse existing routes were the solid lead weights.</p>
<p>Yes, the plan was too perfect. To the nobles, it required no massive upfront investment, bore no political risk of exploring the unknown, and promised quick returns. And if anything went wrong, it could be dismissed as the personal actions of subordinate merchants.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Young man,&rdquo; Duke de Guzman looked at me, tossing me a scrap of conversation like charity. &ldquo;You are too young. You must ask yourself more often what the country needs right now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I agreed meekly, yet I didn&rsquo;t believe the Portuguese were fools. But I wavered—the current situation did seem to demand profit as the core objective. Was exploration truly right? Remembering the nobles&rsquo; skepticism, I felt lost.</p>
<p>Sure enough, a year passed, and all of Santa Fe was immersed in a sweet poison named &ldquo;Following.&rdquo;</p>
<p>One only needed to trail behind the fleets flying the Portuguese flag, dock at the ports they had supplied, sweep up spices for a slightly higher price, and offload rugs and muskets for a slightly lower price, to bring ships full of gold back home. There was no need for navigators who could read the stars; the Spanish captains now only needed to learn one skill—watching the Portuguese masts.</p>
<p>In the Royal Shipyard of Seville, oak originally meant for keels was hauled to the court for new dance floors; the best sailcloth was used for ladies&rsquo; sunshades, because &ldquo;since we don&rsquo;t need to cross the ocean, we don&rsquo;t need such sturdy keels and sails.&rdquo; The old shipwrights were fired, replaced by a group of painters skilled in lacquer. These painters dragged old coastal fishing boats ashore, painted them in bright colors, hung the most ornate Spanish royal crests on them, and carved giant lions for the prows—even though the wood inside the lions was already hollowed out by worms.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is called &lsquo;Overtaking on the Bend&rsquo;.&rdquo; Duke de Guzman once told me proudly after some wine, &ldquo;We bear no risk of the storm, yet enjoy the calm after it passes.&rdquo; Beside him sat Master Zheng, smiling with satisfaction. I was drowned in the laughter of Santa Fe, watching through the window as the heathen city of Granada, with its solid walls, was slowly leveled by the Spanish army. Cannons could indeed breach the stone walls of Granada, but as we demolished their walls, we built a higher one in our own hearts. Inside this wall, there was no need for thought or adventure, only following.</p>
<p>Finally, one day, the special envoy of King John II of Portugal stood before Queen Isabella, burning with rage.</p>
<p>I will never forget that scene. The envoy slammed a roll of parchment—the Treaty of Alcáçovas we had signed long ago—onto the table, roaring that our actions were &ldquo;vile thievery.&rdquo; They had detained all our smuggling ships and threatened to completely cut off all our routes south of the Azores. If we wanted to avoid war, we had to pay an astronomical sum in reparations.</p>
<p>That compensation not only wiped out all the profits from two years of the Master’s &ldquo;Borrowing a Hen&rdquo; scheme but also saddled the treasury with a deficit heavier than that of the Granada campaign.</p>
<p>It was the same hall, but the atmosphere was more suffocating than two years prior. Master Zheng was behind closed doors, claiming illness; the wisdom of his homeland surely told him to &ldquo;stay away from a place of trouble.&rdquo; Duke de Guzman looked ten years older. He could no longer look at me with scrutiny, but rather with the expression of a desperate gambler with no cards left to play.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Young man&hellip; that plan to go West you mentioned,&rdquo; the Duke’s voice was hoarse. &ldquo;How much money does it need?&rdquo;</p>
<p>A wave of tragic pleasure rose in my heart, interlaced with helplessness, blending into a bitterness like roasted coffee. &ldquo;My Lord Duke, if you had asked me a year ago, I would have swiftly prepared three brand-new Caravels and eighty elite sailors.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I paused, looking around at these nobles with their ashen faces, and cruelly unveiled the words they couldn&rsquo;t say: &ldquo;But now? We have no money to build new ships, and no time. The Portuguese have blockaded the road south; we can only go West. The giant ships capable of crossing oceans that we didn&rsquo;t build to save money, the mindset of earning from known routes formed back then—these have now become the noose around our necks.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I can only give you three ships,&rdquo; Duke de Guzman gritted his teeth, every word slicing flesh from his own body. &ldquo;The Santa Maria, plus the Pinta and the Niña. This is the absolute limit we can scrape together. The other trade ships have been seized by the Portuguese.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I almost laughed out loud. Those three ships? The Santa Maria was a clumsy cargo ship, slow and sluggish; the other two were little more than oversized fishing boats. This was all they had for me to conquer the unknown ocean. When they had a choice, they embraced the so-called path of &ldquo;borrowing,&rdquo; relying on late-mover advantages and petty theft. And when caught, they remembered that their backbone had always been given by the Portuguese. They could only seek miracles in the weak mud of their own making.</p>
<p>I couldn&rsquo;t say these words. My emotions finally converged into a disheartened response.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes. May God bless us.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I stepped onto the clumsy cargo ship named Santa Maria. It creaked like an old man with arthritis. In my hand was an expired chart—drawn based on Portuguese knowledge from twenty years ago—and I didn&rsquo;t even have a precise compass. The moment the ship vanished into the darkness, I looked back. The walls of Santa Fe still stood tall. We had breached Granada, yet locked ourselves inside a yet stronger fortress. In that city, there were no stars or vast seas, only shrewd calculations and endless following.</p>
<p>NCC woke with a start. There was a lecture by a professor on paper writing this morning. When he rushed in, the professor was using a cyber-style PowerPoint to expound on Artificial Intelligence.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Students, do not think about how to train a foundation model from scratch. That is for OpenAI and Google. That is a bottomless pit of burning money, an &lsquo;unknown risk,&rsquo; and you will absolutely not get research funding for it.&rdquo; The professor paused, pushing up his glasses. &ldquo;What we need to do is Application-Layer Innovation, it is Prompt Engineering. As long as we call their APIs and add our own UI, we can achieve&hellip; Overtaking on the Bend, at the lowest cost.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A burst of cheerful laughter erupted in the classroom—the knowing laughter that belonged to smart people.</p>
<p>The students took notes earnestly, while the &ldquo;AI Rapid Paper Writing Mind Map&rdquo; sent by the counselor in the group chat was downloaded hundreds of times.</p>
<p>Listening to these familiar words, watching events that seemed to have happened in the past, NCC&rsquo;s thoughts drifted further and further away on the Atlantic Ocean. Left behind in the distance were only Master Zheng, the besieged city of Santa Fe, and the nobles who remained trapped inside, waiting for someone else to open up new routes for them.</p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Price of Spine</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/strange_dream_price_of_spine/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 21:11:58 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/strange_dream_price_of_spine/</guid>
      
      <description>He mocks her loss of dignity, only to realize he is doing the exact same thing. A story about how, across centuries, we all stick a &#39;For Sale&#39; sign on our heads, calling it survival.</description>
      
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p><strong>The 15th Year of the Chongzhen Reign (1642).</strong><br>
The markets were desolate, and silver was becoming increasingly precious. The hearts of the people were restless; everyone sought to find a non-sinking beam for themselves atop a collapsing edifice.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;The Spring Bliss Pavilion&rdquo; (Chunxi Pavilion) on the Qinhuai River in Jinling was a place a silk merchant from Suzhou and Hangzhou like myself was obliged to visit. Outside the tower echoed the weeping water sounds of the Qinhuai, unchanged for a thousand years; inside, however, was a suffocatingly warm breeze, a mixture of precious ambergris incense and the stench of cheap liquor. A single banquet hosted here could settle more business than a month of hard toil in the shop. Tonight, I was entertaining Registrar Wang from the Jiangning County Office. I had specially chosen a private booth overlooking the river, where one could see the flickering lights upon the water. We were separated from a box seat booked by a newly risen power only by a screen of speckled bamboo painted with the motif &ldquo;Seeking Plum Blossoms in the Snow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>During the meal, we spoke of our respective bright futures, as if by speaking loudly enough, those soap bubbles could turn into mountains of gold and silver. From the neighboring booth, a coarse, booming voice was pontificating. Hearing the flattery of his sycophants, I realized it was the newly appointed Battalion Commander Wang of the Imperial Guard (<em>Jinyiwei</em>). Originally a salt merchant from Yangzhou, he had somehow found a connection and now wore the prestigious Flying Fish Robe. The people at his table hailed him as &ldquo;My Lord&rdquo; with every breath, a tide of obsequious praise. I chuckled inwardly; it seems that when people in this world strip off their outer robes, the insides are all the same.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This humble one knows a little of the art of physiognomy,&rdquo; I said, raising my cup and leaning toward Registrar Wang. &ldquo;Observing Your Honor&rsquo;s aura, your forehead is full and broad, and your glabella glows red. Who is to say that one day you will not ascend the Hall of Audience and become a Grand Minister?&rdquo;<br>
Registrar Wang found this immensely pleasing. Twisting his beard, he waved his hands repeatedly, mouthing humble denials of &ldquo;I dare not, I dare not,&rdquo; yet he drained his cup in one gulp, quickly becoming flushed with drink.</p>
<p>When the waiter brought fresh wine, Registrar Wang, perhaps finding mere drinking dull, raised his voice and shouted downstairs: &ldquo;Invite Miss Suxue up here! Have her sing two songs for me and Master Nan to liven things up!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Before long, the beaded curtains rustled lightly, and a woman dressed in a moon-white tunic walked slowly in. This was Suxue. She cradled a seven-stringed zither in her arms. Her figure was slender, and though her brows held the customary docility of the pleasure quarters, there was a hidden coolness in her eyes—like the concealed tip of a brush in calligraphy, or a flower blooming amidst dense leaves. Unlike the other girls in the pavilion who were heavily rouged, she wore only a small white pearl flower in her hair, giving her an air of scholarly elegance. Rumor had it she was the daughter of an Imperial Censor of the Donglin Faction in the capital who had been stripped of his post; she was well-versed in music, chess, calligraphy, and painting. Since coming to Jinling, she had become the top courtesan of the Spring Bliss Tower. But the times were bad these last two years; guests either indulged in carnal pleasures with famous prostitutes or were too consumed by worry to be entertained. It was rare for her to perform even one song a day.</p>
<p>She bowed gracefully before Registrar Wang and me, saying softly, &ldquo;Greetings, Master Wang, Master Nan.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Registrar Wang, likely wanting to show off his &ldquo;refinement&rdquo; in front of me, waved his hand. &ldquo;Miss Suxue, no need for formalities. I have long heard that your rendition of <em>&lsquo;Mist and Clouds over the Xiao and Xiang Rivers&rsquo;</em> is unrivaled in Qinhuai. Would you trouble yourself to play it for us today?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>&lsquo;Mist and Clouds over the Xiao and Xiang Rivers&rsquo;</em> is a masterpiece of the <em>guqin</em>, lofty in artistic conception and a supreme test of finger technique and state of mind. Upon hearing this, a light flashed in Suxue&rsquo;s eyes, as if she had found a kindred spirit. She solemnly placed the zither on the table, tested the tone, and then, with a light pluck of her pale fingers, a string of notes clear as pearls rolling on a jade plate flowed forth. As the music rose, the greasy vulgarity of the private room seemed to be washed away, and even my mind involuntarily settled into calm. The sound was soft as the mist of the Xiao and Xiang waters, slowly rising to shroud the Nine Doubts Mountain.</p>
<p>Before the section &ldquo;Mist and Rain over Dongting Lake&rdquo; was finished, just as the mood was entering its finest realm, the coarse voice of Battalion Commander Wang from behind the screen next door exploded:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Stop, stop, stop! Who are you playing this rubbish for? Bland and tasteless, it’s putting me to sleep!&rdquo;</p>
<p>With one shout, the music stopped abruptly, like a silk thread snapped by force.</p>
<p>Suxue&rsquo;s fingertips froze on the strings. I saw her back straighten instantly, and the blood drained from her face. The booth fell into a deathly silence; even the sound of cups and chopsticks clinking ceased.</p>
<p>Battalion Commander Wang seemed extremely satisfied with this effect. He laughed loudly, &ldquo;I&rsquo;m in high spirits today, and I don&rsquo;t want to hear this old, toothless, mournful trash! Come on, sing me the popular tune <em>&lsquo;The Hanging Branch&rsquo;</em>. Sing it well, and this Lord will reward you heavily!&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>&lsquo;The Hanging Branch&rsquo;</em> was the most popular vulgar ditty in the streets; its lyrics were bold and its tune frivolous—the favorite side dish for lechers. To ask Suxue, known for her purity and elegance, to sing this was tantamount to slapping her face in public.</p>
<p>I saw Suxue lower her head, motionless for a long time. Her hand resting on the zither showed knuckles turning white. I could feel the stormy seas raging in her heart. Registrar Wang&rsquo;s face turned green then white; he wanted to say something diplomatic, but fearing the power of the Imperial Guard, he dared not utter a word.</p>
<p>&ldquo;What&rsquo;s the matter? Will you play or not?&rdquo; Battalion Commander Wang said impatiently, casually tossing two ingots of silver onto the floor. The heavy silver hit the floorboards with a dull thud. The sound struck our hearts like a drumbeat.</p>
<p>Just as I thought she would flick her sleeves and leave, she slowly raised her head. The humiliation and struggle on her face had been tidied away completely, replaced by a nearly perfect, professional, charming smile.<br>
&ldquo;It was this slave&rsquo;s lack of tact to disturb Commander Wang&rsquo;s elegance,&rdquo; she parted her red lips, her voice so steady not a ripple could be heard. &ldquo;I shall sing <em>&lsquo;The Hanging Branch&rsquo;</em> for My Lord.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She gently pushed the simple <em>guqin</em> aside, as if pushing away another version of herself. Then she stood up, abandoning even the instrument. Beating time with her hand on the edge of the table, she began to sing crookedly to that frivolous rhythm. She sang extremely well; every turn of the melody carried just the right amount of seductive implication. Her eyes wandered, her posture alluring; she possessed more amorous flair than any girl in the tower who specialized in bawdy tunes.</p>
<p>Next door, Battalion Commander Wang and his crowd erupted in cheers and obscene teasing, throwing reward money like rain. When the song ended, Suxue adjusted her dress and bowed, then slowly bent down to pick up the broken silver and copper coins one by one. Facing their mockery, she simply smiled slightly and said, &ldquo;My Lords jest,&rdquo; before bending down to continue picking up the money.</p>
<p>Registrar Wang gave a few dry laughs, trying to blend his laughter with theirs. He brought the wine cup to his lips, but in the end, he could not drink it.</p>
<p>I, however, could no longer hear the clamor. My gaze was fixed solely on her smiling face. That smile was like a wooden mask at a temple fair, hiding even the tears.</p>
<p>In that moment, I thought of myself.</p>
<p>I remembered a few days ago, in order to obtain a warrant from the Governor of Yingtian, I presented the only heirloom left by my late father—a Song Dynasty Duan inkstone I had treasured for years—to Advisor Zhang, who loved calligraphy. Advisor Zhang took the inkstone, glanced at it casually, and then used it to weigh down a piece of paper written with a greasy menu. Was the smile hanging on my face then not exactly the same as Suxue&rsquo;s humble and sincere smile now?</p>
<p>She pushed away the <em>guqin</em> for silver. I offered up the inkstone for my future.<br>
So it is; we are the same. In this turbid world, we have all inserted a <strong>straw mark</strong> on ourselves, waiting for someone to ask the price.<br>
The only difference is that she sells the elegance within the zither&rsquo;s song, while I sell the pitiful ideals in my heart. Our &ldquo;moral bones&rdquo; were broken and defiled by a <em>&lsquo;Hanging Branch&rsquo;</em> and a greasy menu.</p>
<p>Laughable! I actually deluded myself into thinking I could use money to buy her momentary smile, to appreciate her &ldquo;character&rdquo;!<br>
In this era, where is there any character left! The moral character spoken of in the sage books has long been stolen and switched by those &ldquo;saints&rdquo; full of benevolence and morality, used to build their own monuments. What is left for us vulgar people rolling in the mud is nothing but a hollowed-out, worthless shell.</p>
<p>Suxue finished gathering the reward money, curtsied towards Battalion Commander Wang&rsquo;s side, and never looked at us again.<br>
Registrar Wang, somewhat dissatisfied, whispered to me, &ldquo;She is just a woman of the wind and dust after all; she has no backbone, playing such tunes for amusement. Let us ignore her.&rdquo; Having said this, he drained the wine he had held at his lips.</p>
<p>I raised my cup and drained it; the wine was more bitter than gall. As cup after cup of clear yet bitter wine went down my stomach, I distinctly saw a <strong>straw mark</strong> stuck in the hair of Suxue as she picked up the money. I looked down into my wine cup, and my reflection showed that I, too, had one on my head. Though when I looked closely, it was only a hairpin.</p>
<p>The straw mark swayed in the wind, its meaning unmistakable:<br>
<strong>&ldquo;This item is for sale; to the highest bidder.&rdquo;</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>NCC kicked his leg violently and woke up. The alarm clock showed 8:00 AM.<br>
The morning light was faint. NCC scrambled to the teaching building, rushing to the Career Guidance Class that started at 8:30. On the podium, a senior student, acting as a representative of outstanding graduates, was passionately sharing his experience: &ldquo;&hellip;Most importantly, we must find a job with dignity and realize our life&rsquo;s value!&rdquo; Thunderous applause erupted from the audience.</p>
<p>The counselor, face beaming with smiles, held up a mobile phone and weaved through the crowd, snapping photos from various &ldquo;positive and uplifting&rdquo; angles, ready to fill the next article for the official WeChat account.</p>
<p>NCC lowered his head and looked at the resume in his hand, just printed and still warm.<br>
Listed there were NCC&rsquo;s GPA, awards, and deliberately embellished internship experiences. To make it look more &ldquo;valuable,&rdquo; every word was weighed, every sentence filled with the utmost humility, just like a songstress at a banquet preparing to sing <em>&lsquo;The Hanging Branch&rsquo;</em> with a thousand twists and turns.</p>
<p>In the entire classroom, only NCC heard, amidst the applause, the dissipating notes of <em>&lsquo;Mist and Clouds over the Xiao and Xiang Rivers&rsquo;</em> and tasted that cup of incredibly bitter wine.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="annotations-for-the-reader">Annotations for the Reader</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chongzhen Year 15 (1642):</strong> The end of the Ming Dynasty. A time of famine, internal rebellion, and external invasion (by the Manchus), characterizing an era of despair and societal collapse.</li>
<li><strong>Jinling / Qinhuai River:</strong> Jinling is an old name for Nanjing. The Qinhuai River was the renowned red-light district, famous not just for sex, but for high-class courtesans who were skilled in arts and poetry.</li>
<li><strong>Jinyiwei (Imperial Guard) &amp; Flying Fish Robe:</strong> The Emperor&rsquo;s secret police and military guard. They were feared for their power to arrest and torture without trial. The &ldquo;Flying Fish Robe&rdquo; was a prestigious uniform granted by the Emperor, symbolizing high status and power.</li>
<li><strong>Donglin Faction:</strong> A group of scholars and officials who advocated for moral integrity and reform. They were brutally purged by corrupt eunuch factions. Being a &ldquo;daughter of the Donglin&rdquo; implies a background of high moral standing and tragedy.</li>
<li><strong>Guqin vs. The Hanging Branch:</strong> The <em>Guqin</em> is a quiet, scholarly instrument associated with high culture and contemplation. <em>&lsquo;The Hanging Branch&rsquo;</em> (<em>Gua Zhi Er</em>) was a genre of popular, often bawdy folk songs. The contrast represents the clash between dignity/art and survival/vulgarity.</li>
<li><strong>Duan Inkstone:</strong> A famous type of stone used for grinding ink, highly prized by scholars. Giving it away symbolizes giving up one&rsquo;s identity as a scholar/gentleman.</li>
<li><strong>The Straw Mark (Cao Biao):</strong> <strong>[Critical Cultural Concept]</strong> In ancient China, when selling items (or even children/people) at a market, a piece of straw or grass inserted into the object or the person&rsquo;s hair signified &ldquo;For Sale.&rdquo; In this story, it is the central metaphor for self-commodification and the loss of dignity.</li>
</ul>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dreams of Gold and Dust</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/strange_dream_gold_and_dust/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 10:08:10 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/strange_dream_gold_and_dust/</guid>
      
      <description>A surreal dialogue on power, and a brutal punchline on reality.
In the dream, an Emperor explains the art of ruling: keep the hawks half-starved, and they will hunt for you with desperate loyalty. In reality, a young man wakes up hungry in a cramped apartment, watches a video of a lavish state banquet, and finds his only satisfaction in attacking a stranger online who dares to criticize the excess.
When physical hunger is silenced by the dopamine of defending the very system that starves you, the cycle is complete.
A short story about the psychology of the downtrodden, and how the &#39;Gold&#39; ensures the &#39;Dust&#39; remains exactly where it belongs. </description>
      
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<p>I am the Emperor.</p>
<p>Night has fallen. An old minister sits across from me.</p>
<p>I flick my long, flowing silk sleeves with practiced elegance, brushing away non-existent dust from the gold-threaded cushion. I have rehearsed this motion a thousand times, every inch of me mimicking the effortless grace of the old aristocracy. Opposite me, the minister sits with a slumped back, his face etched with exhaustion and disappointment. Yet, the natural dignity in his posture makes my heart sink. My elegance feels like the painted mask of an actor; beneath it reeks of insecurity.</p>
<p>In that moment, I am once again the peasant boy frantically scrubbing mud from his skin, while he—he is the true nobleman of spirit.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your Majesty,&rdquo; he begins, his voice raspy like sandpaper. &ldquo;Years ago, you and I scraped for food in the mud. We suffered under crushing taxes and famine until we risked our heads to rebel. Now that you sit upon the Dragon Throne&hellip; do you still remember those days?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I frown, impatient. The past is a rot I wish to cut away. Just a momentary reminder makes me feel that familiar, acidic stench of poverty. When I first took the capital, I would wake up screaming, terrified that this palace was just a handful of sand, ready to slip through my fingers. To banish that fear, I built grander monuments and wrapped myself in majestic robes, trying to murder the memory of that &ldquo;poor boy.&rdquo; His mention of the past isn&rsquo;t nostalgia; it&rsquo;s an flaying of my skin.</p>
<p>I let out a cold, dismissive snort.</p>
<p>The minister, expecting this, persists stubbornly. &ldquo;You once promised to rule like the Sages, to save the people from hanging by their heels. But this new &lsquo;Palace Tax&rsquo;&hellip; I fear it is not a blessing for the realm, nor your original intent.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I shift my gaze from the bronze charcoal burner-fueled by expensive, smokeless silver charcoal-to his face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am establishing authority for the sake of the realm,&rdquo; I interrupt him slowly, my tone dripping with a condescending pity. &ldquo;You only see the suffering of the peasants, but you do not understand the weight of &lsquo;Dignity.&rsquo; If I lived in a hut and wore rags, how would the barbarians view our Great Empire? My towers of jade and gold are not merely for my pleasure; they are the Face of the Nation. I bear the burden of this luxury for them. They contribute a little grain to support the dignity of the State—should they not be grateful?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The minister freezes, clearly stunned by my audacious logic.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The boat is floated by water&hellip;&rdquo; He tries to quote the ancient proverb to warn me, hinting at rebellion without daring to call me a tyrant.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Water floats the ship, but it can also swallow it. I know.&rdquo; I cut him off, a cruel, playful smile curling my lips. &ldquo;Old friend, you have read too many books and forgotten how life works. When I toured the North, I watched the falconers. Even an illiterate trainer knows the truth: If you feed a hawk until it is full, it will not hunt. It might even peck out its master&rsquo;s eyes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I lean forward, savouring the blood draining from his face.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is only when they are half-starved, eyes fixed desperately on that tiny scrap of meat dangling in the air, that they will fight to the death for their master.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&quot; The commoners are my hawks. Keep them barely fed, just enough to prevent starvation, and they will kneel in tears of gratitude for every crumb. If they become too comfortable, they breed dangerous thoughts. I am disciplining their nature, saving them from the chaos of their own desires. This&hellip; is my greatest mercy.&quot;</p>
<p>The light in the minister&rsquo;s eyes dies. He looks at me as if I were a stranger, a monster. The bond of sharing a moldy crust of bread in the rain years ago is now covered in dust—thick, choking dust. I look back, hiding the sudden hollowness in my chest behind a mask of imperial arrogance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As for your history books,&rdquo; I stand up, enjoying the height advantage, &ldquo;History is written by men like me. Centuries from now, my tablet will rest in the Royal Temple. The scribes will record me as a Sage Emperor who brought rain and prosperity. And the groans from the mud? Hah. The wind blows, and they are gone. Who remembers the dirt? I am the Gold; they are the Dust. Is that not obvious?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The minister seems to shrink, his spirit hollowed out. He bows his head deeply, and for a long, long time, says nothing more.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p>The dream ends.</p>
<p>Sunlight stabs through the gap in the curtains, piercing the gloom of the room. In that single pillar of light, countless specks of dust fly blindly, smashing into each other in their tiny, chaotic world. But who cares about dust?</p>
<p>My stomach lets out a long, hollow growl. A burning emptiness twists inside me. I’ve been waking up starving lately—probably because I skipped dinner again to save on the commute fare. I instinctively grab my phone, letting the harsh screen light wash over my face, desperate for a hit of dopamine to numb the reality of this peeling, rented room.</p>
<p>My finger scrolls mechanically. A short video pops up: A Grand State Banquet.</p>
<p>Red carpets stretch like rivers of blood. Golden chalices are raised high. The music is triumphant, grandiose, nearly blowing out my cheap phone speakers.</p>
<p>I stare at the screen, at the grease glistening on the roasted meats. My Adam&rsquo;s apple bobs. I swallow hard, gulping down saliva that isn&rsquo;t there.</p>
<p>Look at that power. Look at that class. It makes me feel&hellip; strangely proud. It makes me straighten my spine, as if I’m sitting at that table, not lying on a lumpy mattress.</p>
<p>I open the comments section. It is a sea of praise and patriotic emojis.</p>
<p>But then, my finger stops.</p>
<p>Someone has posted an untimely complaint, whining about the cost, about how hard it is for normal people to buy groceries. That single line of text sits there, lonely and jarring amidst the golden chorus. Like a piece of grit in the eye.</p>
<p>My fingers, previously weak from hunger, suddenly tense up. A surge of nameless rage ignites in my chest. What does this loser know? Spilling cold water on such a magnificent day? He is ruining the vibe. He is ruining my moment of vicarious glory.</p>
<p>Like a beast catching the scent of prey, I attack.</p>
<p>My thumbs fly across the glass screen, tapping out a frantic tat-tat-tat that echoes in the silent, empty apartment. I type, delete, and retype, sharpening my words into shivs. I need to hurt him. I need to humiliate this ungrateful wretch who can&rsquo;t see the Big Picture.</p>
<p>Send.</p>
<p>Then, I tap his profile. Report. Reason: &ldquo;Hate Speech / Inciting Conflict.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I watch the little loading circle spin, then vanish into a &ldquo;Thank You&rdquo; checkmark. I let out a long breath of turbid air.</p>
<p>Strange. My stomach isn&rsquo;t growling anymore.</p>
<p>That burning hunger has been completely filled by the savage thrill of the cyber-kill. It feels heavy and satisfying in my gut, as if I have just swallowed a chunk of raw, bloody meat.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Some people just need to be taught a lesson,&rdquo; I mutter.</p>
<p>I turn off the screen. The room plunges back into greyness. Only the dust in the sunbeam continues its tireless, blind dance.</p>
<p>I roll over, pulling the damp quilt over my head, and sink back into the comforting darkness.</p>
]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>